I'm calling this the renaissance of
development. If you didn't do VIP
coding, you need to set up your Maven
project. Just setting up the build
environment can already take you a
couple of days to make that work. And
with VIP coding, it just creates that
for you very rapidly. The project I've
done in more or less 5 weeks now. It
would have taken me definitely three
people 6 months without doing VIP
coding. So after 4 months of waiting, I
decided to develop my own plug-in in
Java which is called DevOps Genie. So I
did the first prototype in React. I used
that as a code to spec and then for my
final implementation I went spec to
code. So it's like a round circle so to
speak and that really helped a lot. And
just last weekend we reached 30,000
downloads already of people using it.
>> If I was to go to people and say who is
Stefan Yansen, people will think ah
Devox pretty much it's the premier uh
Java conference worldwide.
>> I do think so. We welcome 20,000
developers every year across a small 20
events of which eight deoxes and 12 10
vox days.
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast's for you.
Now, we've had amazing guests like
Olivier Pomel, the CEO of Data Dog,
Matty Stanisowski, the co-founder of 11
Labs, Victor Ripelli, the CEO and
co-founder at Synthesia, and of course,
Tesla's very own Patrick Dubois. And
they're all sharing lessons right from
the frontier of our industry. A really
quick ask, 90% of people who are
listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. It
really does help us keep bringing the
folks who are actually pushing this
space forward and helping build that AI
native future. All right, back to the
episode. Hello and welcome to the AI
Native Dev podcast. Uh my name is Simon
Maple and on joining me on this episode
is uh Stefan. Stefan, how are you?
>> I'm very good, Simon, thank you. And
Stefan, you are the what is your
official title, Stefan? You're head of
Devox. Oh,
>> head is a I I founded Devox or Java
Polish uh in 2001
and I basically run the Devox Belgium
edition. Um and I try to get at least
the coordination or know what's
happening in the other Devoxes and Vox
days which I co-ounded with Mark Hazel.
>> Yeah, absolutely. and and so
Javopouloolis which is now DevOps um
I'll go as far as to say pretty much
it's the premier uh Java conference
worldwide I think it's it's reasonably
fair to say probably the biggest Java
based uh uh group of conferences across
the world as well
>> I do think so I mean we welcome 20,000
developers every year across a small 20
events of which eight deoxes and 12 10
vox
So if you group them together, it's a
substantial amount of developers that we
reach uh every year.
>> Absolutely. It's incredible. And and of
course, I would say your flagship event
is probably as as you just mentioned
there, Belgium. Um it's it's an event
which has three and a half thousand
folks come to Antworp every year in in
October. Um in fact, Tesla are very very
happily sponsoring this year and we have
a we have a couple of sessions there as
well. So really looking forward to that
in in October this year. And we were
talking off air just then how fast the
tickets go. It's basically like a rock
concert, right? It's seconds and all
tickets disappear. It's pretty
incredible.
>> It's It's crazy. I mean, because of
that, we do two batches. So we have one
batch last Monday and then another batch
on the 1st of September because we have
actually people calling us crying
literally crying on the phone saying
like my boss told me to get 10 tickets
and I didn't get even in. So for those
type of scenarios at least we have a
second smaller batch to to you know uh
solve some some issues from
registration's point of view. But it's
just crazy. I mean, we had 4,600 unique
IP addresses refreshing before the
registration went open and then people
just jump on those. Um, just crazy. But
luckily, I mean, people do release them
once they have like a conference ticket.
They still do release some tickets. So,
currently we still have deep dive
tickets and comi tickets. Uh, but the
conference tickets, they're all gone.
>> It's it's absolutely incredible. I like
particularly postcoid as well. I hear so
many conferences that are not struggling
necessarily, but they definitely see a
dip. Um, and I'm sure it's probably
similar with yourself, but it's
incredible to see that that demand is
still so high for the for the kind of
like what I would call I guess the the
the premium conference, the highest uh
the hardest conference to get in, not
just as a speaker, but definitely as a
as a participant. I think a lot of
people at companies because they work at
home after co a lot of them use it also
as a social gathering where they're get
together for five days you know go to
great talks and in the evening have a
beer or two and talk about tech so you
know it's a great uh week having fun
>> uh incredible so when we say like if I
was to go to people and say who is
Stefan Yansen people will think uh Devox
it's like oh he yeah he runs Devox he he
he he hosts and runs Devox Belgium Jim,
but behind all that, you you're a very
active developer. You've been tinkering
with AI dev tools and and things like
that for actually, you know, a
significant amount of time. This isn't
something that you've just got into. I
think I've been following on Twitter for
for for ages and and and you've been
like playing with lots of lots of stuff
like loads of image recognition stuff in
the early kind earlier days. I remember
was it basketball you were kind of I
remember all that kind of cool stuff.
What have you been doing more recently?
>> Well, the beauty of organizing DevOps
Belgium, it's not a full-time job. You
know, it it gradually picks up in pace
and like now the last months it's really
hectic. But once Devox Belgium is
finished, I have like four, five months
where I can just do pure research and
development and tinkering as you said
with with different tooling and and
frameworks and things that I saw at
DevOps which inspires me and then I want
to play with it. And one of those things
was two years ago. I mean, Jet Brains
announced this AI assistant uh and they
actually demoed it at Devox Belgium
during the opening keynote. And one of
my questions to Anton was like, hey,
does it work with local models? Is it
open source? Uh can I choose any other
cloud model? And those answers were
constantly negative. So after four
months of waiting um I decided to
develop my own plug-in which I've never
done before using um you know in Java.
So I wanted to build a fully open-source
Java plug-in for code assistance which
is called Devox Genie. And just last
weekend we reached 30,000 so 30,000
downloads already of people using it.
And the aim was to really support local
models. like Lama, LM Studio, YAN, Lama
CPP, all of those, but also the cloud
models. And the crazy thing is is that
you can switch between the different
models. So you can work first with a,
for example, local model, then have a
cloud model, review the local model
response, etc. And that's what I I've
been working on quite a bit for the last
eight months or so. Um and then of
course there were other tools coming out
especially CLI command line interface
tools like cloth codes and so you know
the DevOps Genie it works people are
using it happy starting to focus a bit
more on the CLI type of tooling uh which
is of course you know code gemini and
codeex I think those are the three
frontier ones and and for me I had like
okay maybe I need to do a new experiment
in July because it's still a bit not too
busy pets. Um, and I decided to do a VIP
coding experiment.
>> This is super interesting. Now, and this
is what the sessions this this uh
podcast episode is going to really be
about. We're going to talk through how
this experiment that you built, and it's
a it's a a neat little app that we're
going to uh we're going to talk through
uh for as a as an assistant, as a helper
to the to the DevOps conference in in
October. And we're going to talk about
the approaches and the tools and the
processes that you use to build this.
Um, you started with uh a traditional
well I say traditional but given vibe
coding has been a term that's been uh
probably only popularized for the last
year or so. You started with that vibe
coding approach using using the kind of
like tradition well using the the the
better of the vibe coding tools I would
say and then you you hit your limits I
guess on on that vibe coding and we'll
talk through what they are and you then
move more into a spec driven approach.
So how can you actually use
specifications that allow the LLM to
kind of like build the same app uh but
but through the specifications and we'll
talk through the various successes and
pain points of each of these. So first
of all Stefan talk us through what this
app is what the need of this of this
application was for you. So we already
have for about two years an also an open
source project called Foxring which was
a tool developed by Fri Caml and
beautiful application it uses Firebase
at the back end etc. But for him, it's
more like a a hobby project, an evening
project. And I was really starting to
miss certain features. For example,
searching speakers, introducing the
photos, which I'm also using face
recognition to show the speaker photos.
Um, and then one of the other more
important features like authentication,
so people could authenticate themselves.
So their favorite could also be shared
on their mobile phone etc. So it's
basically the the Devox companion
application, which I I said like, okay,
you know what? I'll try to redevelop
that using just f coding. And the the
the limitation was really I do not touch
any code. I can look at it, but I can
only prompt it. That was the limitation
I I enforced myself,
>> which really is what vibe coding is,
right? It's it's it's you code and you
you you're effectively well, I suppose
you're using you're using your vibe or
you're using those small messages to
kind of like suggest changes, but a lot
of that is really you are testing
through almost click. you're not
necessarily, you know, creating, well,
you could, I guess, build a number of
tests, but it's typically not how things
are done. People will typically say, I
need this change, it makes that change,
you test that change just through
clicking around and and with an app with
a front end. Is is that typically how
you is that typically your flow?
>> Yes. So, well, the other limitation I
said is that I will do it in React,
which I don't really know. So that
already forced me to not even look at
the code because I don't know React that
I've never done a React application.
>> And the reason you used React there, the
reason that choice was made wasn't
because of a technical choice. It was
because you didn't know it.
>> Two things because I don't know it. And
I've seen other VIP coding posts and
people do know that React is very well
indexed by these LLM. So the LLMs really
know it very well. you know, if you go
to more exotic languages like Go or or
maybe Rust, you might not have that much
support from the frontier LLMs, but
React is up there, you know, one of the
top technologies supported. And so that
that was how I wanted to start. And and
so um I already had of course some
features in my head of how the existing
application was that I wanted to mimic,
but I wanted to go beyond. And what you
really see is that in the first couple
of days you get an enormous boost. I
mean the the the UI that it creates the
first thing is like you know it creates
a design that a backend developer I'm
more a backend developer I could never
produce such a beautiful design and then
if you do look at the CSS you know the
CSS is beautifully done it's responsive
etc. So you get an enormous boost
immediately. Um and so I spent two weeks
doing pure vibe coding and I must say I
got all the way till 90% of the
functionality. Uh but the last 10% it
was really struggling and then I started
to to look closer of like what's
happening and doing more like um
reflection type of prompts and what I
noticed is that well there were a couple
of things. One was like I was ah I need
to support dark and light themes. So in
a way they was refactoring the the the
CSS to support with variables to support
dark and light. Then I was like oh I
need to support internationalization. So
then it was introducing resource
bundance and so on. Then I was already
starting using Firebase but then you go
like okay I need fire store I need
storage maybe I want to do the real time
database. So you're basically
prototyping and refactor or letting the
LLM refactor your code based on your
chains requirements. Um so that wasn't
cut stone before I started. So that
might have also resulted in a few
strange behaviors but nevertheless after
two weeks 90% worked 10% of the
application was really broken and what
it's uh after some investigation it had
created too many redirections and too
many abstraction layers that it was just
basically spaghetti code. um it could
really not be deployed to production
because it was not fast enough. It had
broken caches etc. And it was basically
I I've basically created a Frankenstein
in two weeks to be honest.
>> Yeah. And and a lot and and a lot of
that is because it's iterative. When you
say Frankenstein, it's because you're
making changes. You're putting whole
extra pieces bolted on almost versus
being built through from scratch. And
that that it's that iterative uh aspect
of it whereby um if a change gets made,
it does its best to to adapt what is
already there versus recognize if it
needs to kind of like you know
regenerate versus things and and and and
do that across an entire application and
build it from scratch as if it were
using that from first principle. I think
you have some things to share as well.
Uh you have the you have the application
uh that we can kind of like we can kind
of like view and talk us through some of
the tools that you used. um as part of
this entire process.
>> So the the tools that I've I've used
throughout the the VIP coding experiment
uh was mainly cloth quotes which which
is a CLI. I bought a $100 subscription
which was actually more than enough. Uh
I must say during that period I did
three blocks of five hours every day. Um
so I wasn't working 15 hours but it was
like three hours then I ran out of
tokens. I had to wait two hours to start
a new uh chunk and so often it was like
you know around 10 hours a day. So those
were long days but very fun uh to do. Um
and so the the that was my main tool
close. uh but then I often actually used
uh especially in the second phase which
we will come back to but in the first
phase sometimes I got stuck um or or the
the prompt didn't find the the solution
and then I had like I went to Gemini and
actually gave Gemini CLI access and
because Gemini is Google Firebase is
Google so it might actually know a bit
better the the documentation around
Firebase it I think two times it
actually helped me uh fix a solution
which cloud cards couldn't uh provide.
So, Gemini definitely helped there and I
just used the API key for that. So, I
was paying per token
and then often I also went to Deepseek
to actually do some brainstorming where
I actually had a chat I gave it to
Deepseek and Deepseek would actually do
some deep thinking or reasoning and come
back uh with some other suggestion or
approaches. Um but that was basically
the first version. uh when I noticed
that I was completely stuck after two
weeks, I actually decided to do a
control alt delete and restart the
experiment uh but now using a technology
that I know a bit better which is
Angular. So that was my my focus. I
would I would redo it in Angular, be a
bit more aggressive in looking at the
code what it produces and really be more
I would say a technical project lead
where I would really guide it and and I
would be the guard rail of what it gets
generated. But what is more important
and I think that definitely helps the
success is that I took the react code as
the basis to create specifications
because the first phase I did not use
any specs I just started prompting um
and but but large prompts but I had no
real specifications. So what I did is
that I fed the react application into
cloth codes and per feature I asked
clothes codes Gemini and sometimes even
chat GPT to come up with a specification
for a certain feature. So having those
three models reviewing each other really
um creates a crystal clear spec for a
specific feature. That feature was then
saved in a markdown in my docs
directory. And so I had a markdown per
feature.
>> And and in terms of that specification,
what would you say were the um the key
the key parts of that specification that
allowed
um you know the next generation of of
the code to effectively um understand
what it needed to to build? Were there
were there headers with specific
information in in each of those
markdowns? Yeah, it was very in it was a
really detailed specification. I mean it
was not only describing the feature but
it would even discuss uh in through for
example the model it would need to use
the even certain snippets of
implementations uh were included. It's
really like it would be a spec if you
give it to a senior developer he or she
would know exactly what to implement. uh
and that was only possible if you have
those three different frontier models
reviewing or even four sometimes
reviewing that. I I I would definitely
recommend having at least minimum two
frontier models reviewing it. But you
have three or four reviewing it and like
Deepseek is even free. I mean I I never
paid for Deepseek and I even used the
the free version of ChachiPT as well. I
only paid for clothes code and Gemini.
But that collaboration between those
four they create beautiful specs uh
which is really sufficient then to take
that and and include it into uh you know
VIP coding uh exercise.
>> Yeah. And it's really interesting the
the the way you talk about it there
where the specification doesn't just so
so one of the ways that we think about
specifications is it separates the the
the what I guess from the application.
Uh whereas today the code uh very often
describes the both the what and the how.
the the the how something should be
written as well as the what it's
actually doing. And it's hard to to kind
of separate those. And it sounds like
what you've done, possibly because you
started from the uh from the from the
the code to generate the specification,
is you've taken that what out of the
code, but peppered it a little bit with
the with the how, I guess. So, you've
got the intentions of what you want the
application to do.
>> Yeah.
>> And then there's then there's pepperings
of the how, which I guess then it pivots
to a specific implementation. Uh but
that's okay if I suspect you know you
only want it to be written in the
application because this is you know an
app specifically for for your needs. I
mean it was exactly I mean I did
basically code well so I did the first
prototype in React. So I had a a first
implementation. I used that as a code to
spec and then for my final
implementation I went spec to code. So
it's like a round you know the round
circle so to speak and that really
helped a lot. Um and and and so there I
I I really saw that the code I mean I
had like also cloth MD file where I said
like okay you need to use
internationalization these are the
languages you need to support I need to
have theming um you you need to use for
example the new iterative for and if
statements in angular etc. So I really
created also a code style specification
how it should behave. I introduced the
llinter. Um and what's I think really
key which is missing up till now in this
story is developing the the testing the
unit tests but also the integration
tests. I didn't do test driven
development. I I I let the VIP LLMs
first create the code. Then I looked at
the functionality visually if it worked.
Then I had it make unit tests. I had it
made integration tests. And those were
just added each time new features were
were developed. And that's really really
key because what you do notice is that
once you start adding a new feature, it
might actually accidentally break
another feature without knowing. And so
you have a new feature but all of a
sudden an older feature is broken. And
if you haven't covered that with a unit
test, you would just you wouldn't know
you wouldn't know that that happened. So
having good integration test and unit
tests really are also your guard rails
to make sure that your VIP coding
doesn't go off rails. Super super
interesting because I think that's what
also a specification allows you when you
state this is what I want my application
to do. It's very easy as part of that
specification to effectively and and
almost maybe even lead with your with
your tests in the specification when you
describe a capability because a
capability can either be written in
natural language as to how you want it
to behave or effectively detailed in
tests which describe its behavior
because you're effectively saying look
when I get this kind of input these are
the types of things I want here are some
here are some kind of like unexpected
outputs that I want you to be able to to
predict and and and and react act in
this way, you're effectively defining
that capability. And and like you say,
um when you make a change, you don't
want that to have a knock-on uh effect
on other parts of the application. And
going back to the to the pure vibe
coding, you know, pre premoving to a
specification. This is the kind of like
problems that you were having with that
10%, right? if there was and I think
you've got a great example of of um you
know when when there was a problem how
it really struggled to to kind of um to
to to find a solution um um you know for
that and it it it lost confidence in
itself. Take us through that.
>> Yeah, that that was really crazy. So I
got stuck uh with cloth code. So, I went
to Gemini because it was a fire fire
store issue and the reaction I got from
Gemini and I'll show you the different
responses is just was really
unbelievable. I mean, as you can see
here, this is incredible frustrating.
It's it replied and I sincerely
apologize for the repeated failures.
It's clear that my approach to modifying
the rules is flawed and I'm not
currently identifying the syntax error.
And it goes on. Then I was just chatting
and said, "No, no, you can find it,
etc." And then he went like, "No, no,
this is beyond embarrassing. I am deeply
sorry for the repeated failures. I'm
clearly not the right tool for this
job." He go like, "Gemini is having an
identity crisis." And it went just back
went back back. And then I said, "No,
no, I'm going to revert the the changes.
I'm really not able to find it." And
then of course I had to step in and
really look at the problem. It was just
one character it had to change in the uh
fire store collection path where you see
here in the first part it has
interactions and an underscore and it
had to be interactions and a slash
>> and it was just both Claude and Gemini
were unable to find that problem.
>> At what point did you feel like an LLM
counselor trying to say no come on
Gemini you are good enough you can do
this.
>> Yeah it's crazy. I mean I I I have seen
online that they've started to fix this
type of apologetic behavior of Gemini.
So I mean they are also Google is also
learning and improving these things and
you can also see that by you know the
different CLI versions that are being
released on an almost daily basis. So
this is just getting better and better
uh for sure. But yeah, that that was
that was very uh was a very I mean the
fact that I took screenshots already
showed you how surprised I was.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and I guess as a user,
you kind of like end up losing
confidence in this kind of thing when it
when it's almost like pleading that it's
it's it's not the right tool and it
can't do it. You as a as a driver of
this kind of a platform or tool lose
massive copy. You start believing it,
thinking, "No, maybe you can't do this.
Maybe I do need to to switch to a
different approach." Now moving to the
to the spec approach when we let's let's
contrast these now because you say of
all of those integration tests those
unit tests and things like that um it
actually provides that much more debug
information and and you know it it
allows it it gives it more of those um
more of those clues as to well okay
what's working not working and
potentially identifies these types of
things in a in a better way right what
what would you say were the major flaws
of um of the kind of like approach of
the vibe coding and what would you say
in spec driven was the key unlocks that
you needed? Was it the tests? Was it
something else? What what what really
was that uh defining moment?
>> Yeah. Well, I mean, if you just do pure
vibe coding and and just some prompting,
it's just way too freestyle. There's no
guardrails. That that's really not
sufficient, right? You need to introduce
these guardrails. And for me the guards
was a good llinter to to start with. So
that the llinter goes through the full
code every time you do a deployment.
That's one. The unit test and the
integration test but also the management
of your specs. Um and I think that's
where there's a huge uh opportunity. I
know you guys are clearly looking into
that. Um what I used was a an
open-source project and I've even
invited the developer I believe he's
from Austria uh to Devox Belgium called
backlo.md
and what backlod does he vcoded that
tube also but you basically install it
locally and it creates like this conbon
uh UI in the browser and there you can
create an issue and then that issue
produces a markdown file and that issue
can then be referenced into cloud codes
where you say okay now work on issue
number one and because you're saying
issue number one it will go to the file
system try to find issue number one MD
which the backlog creates and it will
then work on that issue but what it also
does is that once it has uh finished
that issue it will document what it has
done and include that documentation into
the existing issue on backlog. So when
you revisit that feature or that issue,
it already knows the original complaint
or feature, what it has done and what it
still needs to be do doing. And it
reminded me a bit of gyra in the good
old days. Um, but this is like a
lightweight version of that locally so
the CLI can access it very rapidly and
updated it and it then moves it from
state of where it says created uh what
is it um working or in progress and
done. So it has like multiple states and
and that definitely helped um because
you have your original regional specs
but this allows you to actually have
conversations on top of that spec or
next to that spec which is a living
document and I think that's definitely
the way to go. Um as a result of course
I I I think it was a month or so uh
Amazon came out with Cairo or Cairo or
Cairo which is also spec to code. I had
a quick look at that. Um, yeah, I wasn't
fully convinced yet, but but it's
definitely obvious that this is a a void
that needs to be filled. Um, and and I
think that type of combination makes it
a bit more interesting because then you
have living documentations and features
and bugs and issues which can be
accessed by the LLM.
>> Yeah. from the the the the the point of
view of being a user, being a developer
in each of these scenarios, you
mentioned how fast you were able to kind
of develop, create, and and and show
something working and show something
actually being able to deliver on your
kind of 80 90% of of functionality.
um for anyone having that feedback and
that fast creation is is extremely fun.
It's it's it's very validating of you
know you being able to kind of like
create. You mentioned that kind of like
top that that ceiling I guess that you
hit after 90%. But from a specdriven
approach, you have to do a lot more of
the the kind of okay, let me write some
stuff in natural language, let me now
think about the tests, let me think
about all these, you know, other things
that you need to do which effectively
will slow you down in that kind of like
rapid application development uh
approach if that's what you were trying
to go for. How did you feel as a
developer um the I guess enjoyment
um of doing vibe coding versus spec
coding? But also from a confidence point
of view from a uh you know being
involved in the process did you did you
have more confidence with one over the
other? Talk to me through that. I'm I'm
calling this the the renaissance of
developments or or you know because you
you clearly are getting lots more uh
enjoyment uh and pleasure of doing these
type of projects because you know if you
didn't do VIP coding you need to set up
your Maven projects. Just setting up the
the build environment can already take
you a couple of days to to make that
work. And with VIP coding you know it it
just creates that for you very rapidly.
you get instant satisfaction so to
speak. Um and and that that feedback
loop is very is much shorter. I think in
general
just for prototyping quick prototyping
this is clearly the way to go. Uh if you
really want to do a real project that
you want to deploy for thousands and
thousands of users you know is VIP
deployment VIP debugging is that is that
the way to go? Um I mean just to to to
tell you or share you some anecdotes. I
mean I had a development environment, I
have a staging environment and I have a
production environment. And so I went
like okay I'm I'm creating a task file.
This task file creates tasks which
allows you to deploy etc. And it
obviously had missed the the settings
from production to staging and when I
was deploying to staging it was actually
deploying to production. So these are
the type of things where you go like oh
wow you know um you you do need to still
have knowledgeable people looking into
what it is producing not only looking at
the codes but also looking at the
scripts etc. uh because I can imagine if
you're a a non- techy guy, a
non-developer doing this stuff, you're
going to run into problems because you
just don't know the scale of what it can
produce and and and you just don't know
all the effects and side effects of
things that you are asking it to do. So
I think being a more senior developer,
it it it makes me definitely be more
productive. I could have never created
the UI that it has produced for me. Um,
I mean that replaces a web designer for
sure. Um, but the project I've now done
in more or less five weeks now because
I've I've been doing this for five
weeks, it would have taken me definitely
three people six months without doing
VIP coding. I'm I'm I'm fully convinced
about that. Um, so it's definitely a
gamecher. it is more productive but you
still need some senior developers
guiding this uh because if you don't
you're going to run into problems for
example like Angular has guard uh rules
so we have routing and you can put
guards in front of the routing if you
don't know that concept you're going to
give access to certain pages u as a
junior or or non techy guy uh without
knowing or you might actually expose
those uh API keys or really security
issues. And that's why I've also did
certain exercises where I said like to
close code, hey, you're a white white
hat hacker. Try to hack my system. And
it actually goes through your codes,
goes to your website and tries to hack
your system. And those are really
valuable exercises because it will
actually highlight, oh, I was able to
see the admin page without being logged
in. Okay. Well, fix it, you know, look
at it and go deeper. Or I did another
exercise where I went I went where I
went like, okay, we have 3,000 unique
users during DevOps Belgium. Uh, how
will the system scale? How will be
performance? Where are the bottlenecks?
And it does this exercise where it
really then goes like well your Firebase
functions, you should have better memory
or more memory, you need to allow more
instances, etc. So having these other
type of discussions which are not so
much development oriented but more
devops oriented is definitely also a
step you need to do within that process.
>> I'd love to break that down a little
further. We there's a couple of things
there that I'd love to talk through. The
first one is you kind of you kind of
alluded to the fact that you need those
senior developers or or people who
really understand have that sympathy of
what is being built, what's happening to
to review essentially or or to make sure
to validate that what is being created
um is actually correct. It's the right
way of doing things. It's the right
implementation so to speak. an amount of
that can be done, I guess, with with
things like tests and things like that.
Um, how how much did you do a lot of
those reviews versus what it sounds like
allowed the the LLMs or different LLMs
to kind of like jump in and do those
reviews for you? Were you comfortable if
you just let DeepSeek or something else
come through and say, "Tell me if this
is okay and I'll trust you." Where was
your limit?
>> No, I I was not fully 100% comfortable
for sure. Um, just this morning I
actually found another bug in the
deployed application now because it's
already being used now by by hundreds
hundreds of people uh for DevOps
Belgium. And so I did a a refactoring
using prompting where the speaker can
actually edit his pictures which are
identified from Flickr using face
recognition and he or she can decide
which picture he wants to show on his
speaker profile. And so that worked, but
it actually broke a feature where the
pictures are not shown anymore uh on the
public page. And I went like what
happened? And so I could not have I mean
I could have only fixed that or
anticipated that with using uh end to
end uh testing using Cypress. I've
chosen Cypress, but I had no test for
that specific scenario. So it basically
broke something in production and where
I went like but to be honest this can
happen also in normal teams without
doing V coding right I mean this is
reality it these things do happen um so
my target is I would love to get a 80%
coverage with the unit tests I would
love to have more end toend testing as
well but that just takes still a lot of
effort even if it's just prompting but
it would increase my confidence that
yeah if I do deploy it and I have those
type of coverages um it it would
increase my confidence to to to move
forward. Um so I think those are
definitely critical to to have um
without you're just walking in a dark
room and you're going to hit your head
against the wall for sure, right? Uh so
I think test driven or or just unit
testing integration testing um is is
becoming more and more important to make
sure to enforce the specs that you've
defined and I think that collaboration
will will be a success combi.
>> Yeah absolutely I guess like going
forward with future development as well
um let's say let me give you a couple of
uh of of scenarios. If you were to
create a new feature, um,
would you create a new spec to do that
or would you update and and append make
changes to an existing specification?
So, I guess the question is
>> the life the the the the lifetime of
your the life cycle of your spec. Does
your spec follow the change or does your
spec follow the application?
>> Yeah, currently not. Um, so the the spec
does not follow any changes that I've
made. um uh which is which is maybe a
flaw in in my process. I should probably
keep it alive and up to date. I do
review and up to I keep the readme up to
date or the cloth.mmd up to date um
because you can easily do that but
having tool tools which would help me
keep that in sync even if it happens in
the background I think that would be
amazing feature to have from a tool
perspective. giving you some hints here,
Simon.
But that would be amazing because now I
have to explicitly say it. I need to
really say, okay, if I want to like this
feature with the broken photos, um, that
should be something which would need to
be covered by some integration test. So
it actually validates that that isn't
broken, but it should be reflected in
the spec. And because I'm lazy or I'm
not thinking about that, the spec gets
out of date. And if there are tools who
would keep that in sync, that would be
amazing. uh for sure. Um and and of
course all these CLI tools they have
rules which they go back to to follow
that uh you know like the claude MD file
or the Gemini MD file etc. Um so there's
definitely still some room for for
improvements but there's huge
opportunities for product companies to
fill that void.
>> Yeah. And so and so you're using
specifications really to um to drive
your development, but it's not
necessarily specentric in the sense of
any change you would make beyond that
initial generation would more likely be
directly into the code versus into the
spec first. Correct.
>> Um and of course, like you say, that
then puts the spec out of out of sync, I
guess. And then it it almost like pushes
you back into that vibe coding mode
versus the the spec centricity that you
found valuable the first time.
>> And I think that's a discipline I need
to change. I need to have the discipline
to actually make sure that the spec kept
is kept into sync and that it's also
always referenced when you start a new
feature or enhance an existing feature.
>> Mhm.
>> Because that's a bit of the problem now
is that you know we used to do I I've
done several talks on rack but what
you're seeing now with these CLI tools
is that I call it file system rack. they
do some kind of you know pattern
recognition on files and the the results
are then injected into the window
context but if certain keywords are not
included in certain specs it might not
actually find these and include it in
the window context so it doesn't know
about it so I think that type of
behavior either the developer should
should have the the discipline to say
hey no always include this specification
like we do now with cloth and the I
actually explicit ly say hey lots load
cloud MD so it's part of the window
context and just yesterday actually
cloud released a new slashcomand called
context where you can see how much of
your window context is used by which
types of documents which is very very
interesting. Um so there's definitely
some some opportunities there to to make
sure that it is included in the window
context either by the developer which
developers are lazy might forget. So I
think tooling should should play a role
there.
>> Yeah. But e even that though even
allowing I even if your code isn't you
know every time directly generated from
the specification allowing giving access
to you know your full set of
specifications to from um you know to to
your agent in this case Claude that that
I'm sure that supercharges the way
Claude makes its changes by truly
understanding the application and how
you know what your intentions are and by
making certain changes knowing okay if I
do that will probably break or whatever.
It's amazing how we talk about it these
days like it's truly thinking like we
are as well. It's it's
>> well it's very knowledgeable, right? I
mean it really does know all the the
syntaxes etc. But the other thing that
just comes into my mind is like I do
feature branches uh on GitHub. So I
create a new feature branch and then I
start working on that. But what actually
would make more sense, I've of course
integrated cloth codes using GitHub
actions into GitHub. But what would make
more sense is that you create first an
issue on GitHub and then use that issue
as your feature branch. But you can have
cloth code codes or any other ALM
already first do some pre-investigation
to actually supplement your feature uh
in GitHub and already use that as your
window context information to start a
feature. And but that's I I believe
currently not possible. It's only be
after the facts. Um but that would be
actually I mean that could be a project
on its own. Um because you then let let
the LLM investigate and see what context
it would need to actually implement that
feature. Then you can start doing the
feature and and it already has the the
context.
>> Yeah. Very interesting. I I I I really
like the the I think context has always
been king and I think what you've also
discussed with the file system context
is very very very very interesting from
that point of view as well. I want to
switch more into the kind of talking a
little bit about maybe some of the
non-functional uh requirements and
aspects and I think this probably maybe
when we when we're using LLMs drops us
into more of a kind of like a rolebased
assessment of what is being built. Um,
so nonfunctional requirements, maybe
it's security, maybe it's performance,
maybe it's availability, these types of
questions. Um, how did you obviously
what you're building right now as a
production application uh that needs to
be needs to be up and alive for the for
you know pre pre-Deox as well as uh
certainly the days of DevOps and then
probably an amount of time afterwards.
um you need to make sure that you know
when 3,500 people are hitting it
potentially potentially you know a lot
of people at the same time for very time
specific things like end of a session
people are going to jump to the schedule
uh maybe do maybe jump to the reviews
and things like that per session um how
do you how does how good is the LLM
without specification I guess or or
rather without you specifying it needs
to be performant it needs to expect a
large number of users at a a specific
time. How good was it without specifying
these are the requirements and and how
did you get it to to um be conscious of
you know these requirements so that when
it's making implementation decisions and
choices it does it in a way that
satisfies these non-functional
requirements.
>> But I think there I'm I'm guilty because
I have of course a bit of experience of
building scalable systems etc. And I I
don't know if you remembered but during
COVID we uh Celestino and I developed
rockets which was an online platform to
do online events etc. And there we we
had the same thing. We had sometimes
thousands of people online using it and
I think just knowing the architectural
choices as a more senior developer plays
a big role there. and and so from the
get-go I immediately said no I want to
use Firebase which is basically Google
cloud right uh I want to use lambdas or
functions um because those are very very
scalable especially if you then run them
on cloud run etc so just that
architectural choice of using firebase
fire store functions or lambdas uh cloud
run etc you already know that if it runs
on GCP it it it can be very scalable
because Google basically
does that for you. So if I would have
started without that knowledge and it
would have maybe created this more fast
API using Python, I might have really
problems, right? Because now it's just a
configuration. I mean you say from the
get-go how many instances you you allow,
what the time out is, what the memory it
gets from functions, and it's it's
basically a stateless function
serverless backends on a scalable cloud
environment. So I could have if I had no
experience at all I could have had
sessions with LLMs asking like what is
the best scalable solution and it might
have come up with that type of
recommendation but for me that was no no
that was a an architectural decision
that I wanted to have from the beginning
knowing that that will scale and I'm
pretty confident it will
>> and it's interesting that you've kind of
alluded to the fact that you know as a
senior Being a developer, there are a
number of choices that you've made that
you know had you not had that experience
in coding perhaps it would they're
nonobvious kind of choices that that you
would potentially make. Um a lot of
people kind of like say well how in the
future are we going to get to those
those senior uh those senior engineers
to know that. Um I kind of question that
a little bit because I feel like well
you know we all have to learn through
our mistakes. We all have to learn
through advice. Um, from advice from an
advice point of view, we we've never
been more capable of asking questions to
whether it's LLMs or people uh through
just because of the the the you know the
new UIs and the new aggregation of data
and information about how to develop,
what good development looks like and so
forth. We're also able to hit our
mistakes quicker because we are able to
vibe code faster, deploy faster. I
question whether the gap is actually
going to be there in the future because
isn't as a junior developer wouldn't I
just make my mistakes faster and get to
that end learning of okay this isn't
scalable I need to use a more scalable
scenario and make you know create those
learnings faster versus as a junior
developer making my code changes and
finding this issue in six months.
>> There's two angles on this. um one is as
a business owner I need a business
solution as fast as possible as cheap as
possible but with quality right and I
think as a business owner having one
senior developer even if it's myself now
in this situation I can achieve that
much faster than if I would have some
juniors um so that's from a business
perspective but if you look at from a
technical point of view as a junior you
now have a universal tutor you have a
coding assistant which is out of this
world so to speak. You can ask all the
questions you want. Even the most
stupidest questions which we would never
have been willing to ask to our
colleagues. You can now ask any question
and you will get really knowledgeable
answers. So if you're a motivated,
dedicated junior developer, you can go
up that ladder and become a senior
developer very fast because you now have
these LLMs which can guide you and help
you. So this is something we didn't
have, you know, a couple of years ago.
Um so you have to be motivated. The only
problem is then the business is the
business willing to actually hire these
juniors and invest in them to become a
senior if I cannot just accomplish a
project with just one senior developer
who would maybe be the project lead of
these of these juniors. So I think
that's a bit of the yeah the the balance
act that that will need to happen moving
forward.
>> Yeah. and and and also as a as a any
developer senior or junior I can kind of
say look to to an LM you are a
performance expert you know you've got
10 20 30 years of of experience in
creating performance systems maybe for a
fintech maybe for a a site that is going
to get huge numbers of of visitors on
specific days
you know add good coding practices for
these types of systems And is that
something that you did with this
application with those types of roles uh
role- based agents I guess?
>> So it was actually uh I think it was
four weeks ago that cloth uh released
soup agents. So what it allows you to do
is actually create a prompt um for an
agent that you give it a name which is
called basically a soup agent and it's
basically a markdown file of a certain
character of a certain profile uh which
it will use when you activate that soup
agent. So you could say like hey you're
for example a tester and you explain
what the tester should do etc. And then
when you actually do a prompt, it will
look into its super agents and activate
that type of avatar, that type of
profile uh where it already sets the
scene of that role and it will behave as
that role for that specific request that
you have.
>> Mh.
>> So that's why also you know for Devox
Belgium I mean our our theme for Devox
Belgium is basically Java agents. Um and
you know we didn't mention that but I
think DevOps Belgium is the biggest AI
conference now because almost 75% are
all about AI large language models but
also using Java on GPU doing inference
on GPUs etc. But mainly the the the
theme if you go to the website it goes
agents and I think that's where the
excitement and the new opportunities are
as well is that you cannot only create
agents in CLIs where it has a certain
role but you can also have asynchronous
agents which work in the background
while you're sleeping or while you're
walking the dog and it's doing certain
actions for you within that specific
role. And that's where it's very
exciting and it's also where even Java
like frames frameworks like lang forj
spring AI they're all going to this next
layer of abstraction which are agents
and I think I think there we're going to
see lots of new innovations happening in
the next 12 months.
>> Absolutely. Now I hate to scare you um
Stefan but what are we now we're
recording this the 22nd of August. Uh
you've got Devox Belgium. Uh what are
the dates of Devox Belgium? Is it 7
>> from the 6th till the 10th of October?
>> 6 to 6 till the 10th of October. Uh so
what are we looking at here? Um about a
month and a half really till till I have
no idea why you're wasting time on
podcasts right now Stefan. You should be
there's probably a ton of stuff you
should be doing uh for DevOps. But in a
month and a half you're going to have
three and a half thousand people
probably more accessing this
application. Uh a lot of them um a lot
of them you know at the same time
accessing the same data. What are your
biggest concerns? Uh, and and I guess
confident confidence-wise, how confident
are you that this app is going to is
going to work flawlessly? What are your
biggest concerns about going live with
this at a major conference?
>> So, I add I added some very interesting
interaction possibilities, new
interaction possibilities. Well, first
is that like people can now finally have
free text comments privately feedback to
the speaker. But what we actually get
often is that there are some less
professional people who enter like okay
certain texts that aren't really
following our code of conduct. So what I
added is that I'm using Gemini Flash 2.5
light to review all the comments and see
if it follows the code of conduct.
>> Nice.
>> Right. And it really even if you're just
using emoticons emojis and they're not
appropriate, it will even find the
emojis say like no this is not following
our code of conduct. Right? So but
that's it works but it's like okay how
will it work if 10,000 people give
feedback? Will it be fast enough? So
those are like concerns I have from that
point of view because it's it's a bit
more difficult to simulate and and
expensive if you want to simulate 2,000
comments at the same time. So th those
are like my biggest concerns. Uh I know
the application will run. I mean it's
Angular. It's hosted on Google Cloud.
It's just JavaScript being returned. So
that's going to work. Fire store is
going to work. I don't see any issues
there. Uh but like I have other things
for example a feature where people can
now say how full the room is. So they
can say the occupancy of the room is
like 90%.
>> And that information is now is now shown
on the digital signage. So you will get
immediately feedback in the digital
signage saying, "Oh yeah, I don't have
to go into that room because it's
packed." And the cool thing about having
that feature is that I don't have to go
because I like to know how many people
are in the room for a certain topic and
speaker. Now if that works, I don't have
to do that anymore. I can just sit at
the registration, look at my dashboard,
and see how full the rooms are based off
communitydriven feedback. kind of feels
like uh you know the how when you do a
Google directions and then it kind of
like says oh yeah this train is busier
than normal and things like that. It's
it's it's exactly that, right? That's
that sounds awesome,
>> but it's communitydriven.
So, the thing is, if that breaks, I'm
going to be vibe coding my
>> you know, I'm trying to fix it on the
spot, of course. And I've got another
crazy feature which I was thinking of
only announcing at the keynote, but I
want to give you the premiere is that I
I vipcoded another feature where I'm
doing uh real time transcripts. So I've
already was doing real-time transcripts
where you see the the transcript on the
screen right I'm already doing that but
now I'm capturing the transcripts from
re real time from this talk and every
two minutes I'm creating the key
takeaways of the talk a cloud keyword
clouds and also a summary of the talk
while the talk is going on
>> amazing
>> so you can go to the mobile app and just
see five minutes in the talk ah these
are the key takeers ways. These are the
keywords he or she is using and that's
the summary. And I'm just hoping that's
going to work. I mean, I've been testing
this, etc., but there's there's a few
moving parts. And that so that's where
I'm going to get nervous. It's like,
will this work?
That's interesting as well because as an
attendee, if I w if I were to see
something like that, I might scroll
through like halfway through a talk, if
I'm not maybe enjoying a talk or if I if
maybe it's like not the right talk for
me, I could actually scroll through and
see what others are talking about what
the summaries are and go, "Oh, actually
that looks really interesting. Let me
let me jump into that one." It gives
people that more that real time that
real time vibe. Super cool.
>> So, I've got real time transcripts and
just imagine what you could do. I could
go even next level. Take that transcript
when the talk is finished, give it to an
LLM and say, "Hey, create a script where
two people are talking to each other."
Then take that script, then go to
OpenAI, create two voices talking to
each other like Notesbook LM is doing. I
could totally do that. Techn taking it
taking from a technology point of view,
that's totally possible. You know, the
only thing is that some speakers have
concerns about that because they don't
like a real podcast from their talk, the
accuracy, etc. So, I've put that in the
fridge for now. But from a technology
point of view, that's just like it's
like science fiction. How the hell, you
know, two years ago that was not even
possible and now you can do that.
>> Let's talk about I want to talk I want
to kind of like finish up with two two
last kind of questions. I want to I was
going to originally we talked a little
bit about the role of of of a developer
a little bit. I want to talk about the
role of a conference Stefan when we talk
about
you know in the day jobopolis moving to
DevOps it was it was a very
languageoriented conference what's what
do you think the future of a langu of a
developer conference looks like because
we've already talked just now about you
know your and I love the I love the
framing of saying you know DevOps is one
of the largest or the largest you know
AI developer conferences in the world
and it's Like do do conferences need to
evolve now? Because as the role of a
developer changes, the skills that a
developer needs to learn to actually
become an effective developer isn't now
or is going to be less and less oriented
around how they use a language or you
know or their capabilities of of whether
it's design or architecture because we
will lean more and more into AI. So is
it more a combination of our best usage
of AI and some of that mechanical
sympathy knowledge of of how
applications should be built? What
what's your vision for DevOps going
forward?
>> Yeah. So I always say I mean I spend
almost nine months producing and
organizing this event and it goes just
like that. It's not full-time nine
months but you know so I I always say
like this is our party you know this
five days event is a party that we
organize where we handp speak and topics
etc and so I want to reflect the content
from the conference where the excitement
is where I'm getting excited
and so my excitement is clearly in AI
with large language models etc and I
want to make sure that that is reflected
in the conference so that's that's one
thing but the other thing is also yeah
if up till now my excitement matches
with the excitement of other developers
and they're curious to learn these new
things etc. And so I think we did pivot
a bit already this year because I
clearly took the card of like okay AI
agents and LLM and coding assistants is
where the buzz is and the excitement is
let's go full-blown for that for Devox
Belgium. And to be honest, on Monday I
was really nervous because I it could be
that people find it as a as a how do you
call that their their job security and
as a danger and they might just be
reacting on the as a oppositely of what
I was going for. Um but it looks like
people are excited about this. They want
to learn.
>> Well, you only had a few seconds to wait
before getting your answer at least.
>> But it's also a reputation a bit, right?
people do know what to expect from
Devox. I mean, we've been doing this for
25 years now. Uh so people know what to
expect. But but you're definitely right.
I I do if you just look at the content
already for this year. There is there's
going to be we we need to embrace this
new possibility and I think the
excitement is there. The productivity is
there as well. There are dangers
involved for sure, but as a conference
that's something we need to highlight uh
make sure that we reflect it from the
speakers and content point of view. I
mean, I I even have Rod Johnson, the
founder of Spring, you know, he lives in
Australia. He's coming over to do a
hands-on lab session. He's doing a
keynote and he's doing a conference talk
about his new AI agent Java framework
called Embab. So, it's like that's where
the excitement is. We want to know
what's possible, etc. And if you reflect
that as a conference, I think you still
have a few additions to to to stay
alive. Um, I've already seen a few other
conferences doing the same strategy in
the US. I mean, they're already going,
okay, yeah, we need to embrace AI. But
what is also interesting, even from a
low-level point of view, there's still
lots to talk about. I mean, we have Paul
Sundos who works on Babylon who is
working on Java and GPU interference. We
have the tornado VM guys from Manchester
University. So there's still lots of
low-level stuff that needs to be
discussed and explored and and and do
knowledge transfer on. So it's going to
be mixture of those two. Uh you might
have people who are no developers at all
who might actually get some benefit of
going to DevOps. But you still have
people who want to know what's under
that layer, what's underneath that
framework, what's actually, you know,
opening up the car as a small boy and
knowing what's in there. I think those
types of people need to be addressed at
a conference.
>> Yeah. And if you do, great. Um, I need
to stay excited and have fun organizing
it. If that stops, then Devox Belgium
will stop for me as well because it's
like I I don't have to do this, right?
Um, and the the only thing I really hate
is that you create this great party, but
I can't really enjoy my own party
because I'm running around like a
headless chicken chicken like from one
fire to the other making sure everything
runs smoothly. Um, and so that's the
biggest disappointment is that I can't
enjoy the conference as a normal Latin
D. Uh, which which is a bit of a shame,
but luckily we record everything so I
can see it online.
>> And I think that's the that's the joy of
it, right? If you know you're enjoying
it, you know there's a really strong,
you know,
>> that's what you would expect.
>> Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. Yeah.
>> And if that stops, it stops. I mean I
mean it would be totally fine to have a
few sobatical years and just doing R&D.
Uh but I don't think we we're at that
point yet.
>> Stefan, I'm I'm sorry to inform you. I
think it's actually going to I think
it's going to grow from here. So, you
know, your job is well safe and and and
yeah, sorry to add more to your plate,
but uh absolutely. Yeah. Cool. Stefan,
this is this has been this has been
brilliant and um a real insight into
kind of like how your um your approach
uh needed to change uh from from
developing an application uh going from
kind of more of a a vibe coding to a
spec driven approach and and fingers
crossed uh DevOps and and and I'm sure
it all go well be another amazing
conference. I'm looking forward to being
there again. I've been there many years
and and looking forward to uh to to to
seeing you in person again and and and
being there in October. So, all the best
for Devox. For those uh for those who
want to check it out more, uh devox.be,
I think, right?
>> Correct.
>> Devox.be and um and yeah, all the best.
Thanks very much, Stefan. It's been a
it's been a joy to chat with you.
>> Thank you for the opportunity and
looking forward to the Tesla product
being released uh in the near future.
>> Thank you. Thank you very much, uh
Stefan. And thanks very much for
listening. Tune in to the next episode.
See you soon.
[Music]